I love my food.
أحب طعامي
And I love information.
وأحب المعلومات
My children usually tell me
أطفالي عادة يخبروني
that one of those passions is a little more apparent than the other.
بان احد هذه الرغبات واضح اكثر بقليل من الاخر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what I want to do in the next eight minutes or so
ولكن ما ساقوم به في الدقائق الثماني التالية او ما يقارب
is to take you through how those passions developed,
هو اخذكم الى كيف تطورت هذه الرغبات
the point in my life when the two passions merged,
النقطة التي في حياتي عندما اندمجت هاتان الرغبتين
the journey of learning that took place from that point.
رحلة التعلم التي بدأت من تلك النقطة
And one idea I want to leave you with today
وفكرة واحدة أريد ان اتركها معكم اليوم
is what would would happen differently in your life
ما الذي كان سيحدث بشكل مختلف في حياتكم
if you saw information the way you saw food?
اذا رأيت المعلومات بنفس الطريقة التي ترى بها الطعام؟
I was born in Calcutta --
لقد ولدت في كالكتا
a family where my father and his father before him
في عائلة ما حيث والدي وابيه من قبله
were journalists,
كانوا صحفيين
and they wrote magazines in the English language.
ولقد كتبوا مجلات باللغة الانجليزية
That was the family business.
هذا كان عمل العائلة
And as a result of that,
ونتيجة لذلك
I grew up with books everywhere around the house.
لقد ترعرعت مع كتب في كل مكان حول المنزل
And I mean books everywhere around the house.
واعني كتب في كل مكان حول المنزل
And that's actually a shop in Calcutta,
وذلك في الواقع متجر في كالكتا
but it's a place where we like our books.
ولكنه مكان فيه احببنا كتبنا
In fact, I've got 38,000 of them now
في الواقع، لقد حصلت على 38,000 منها
and no Kindle in sight.
وليس هناك أي كندل على مرأى
But growing up as a child with the books around everywhere,
ولكن النضج كطفل مع كتب في كل مكان
with people to talk to about those books,
مع أشخاص للتحدث معهم حول هذه الكتب
this wasn't a sort of slightly learned thing.
هذا لم يكن شئ تعليمي نوعا ما
By the time I was 18, I had a deep passion for books.
حينما كنت في 18، كان لديّ شغف شديد بالكتب
It wasn't the only passion I had.
لم يكن الشغف الوحيد لديّ حينئذ.
I was a South Indian
لقد كنت هندي جنوبي
brought up in Bengal.
تربيت وسط البنغال
And two of the things about Bengal:
أمرين حول البنغال :
they like their savory dishes
يحبون أطباقهم اللذيذة
and they like their sweets.
ويحبون حلوياتهم
So by the time I grew up,
لذلك مع الوقت الذي ترعرت فيه،
again, I had a well-established passion for food.
مرة اخرى، لقد ملكت رغبة راسخة للطعام
Now I was growing up in the late '60s and early '70s,
والآن لقد نشأت في أواخر الستينات وأوائل السبعينات،
and there were a number of other passions I was also interested in,
وكان هناك العدد من المشاعر الأخرى كنت مهتم بها أيضا،
but these two were the ones that differentiated me.
ولكن هاتان هما اللتان ميزتني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then life was fine, dandy.
وثم الحياة على ما يرام، ممتازة.
Everything was okay,
وكان كل شيء حسنا،
until I got to about the age of 26,
حتى وصلت إلى عمر 26،
and I went to a movie called "Short Circuit."
وذهبت إلى فيلم يسمى "دارة قصيرة"
Oh, some of you have seen it.
أوه، البعض منكم قد شاهده.
And apparently it's being remade right now
ويبدو أنه يصنع مجدد الآن
and it's going to be coming out next year.
وسوف يخرج في العام القادم.
It's the story of this experimental robot
أنها قصة هذا الروبوت التجريبي
which got electrocuted and found a life.
الذي صعقته الكهرباء وعثر على حياة.
And as it ran, this thing was saying, "Give me input. Give me input."
وما ان اشتغل،كان هذا الشئ يقول،" أعطني مدخلات، أعطني مدخلات"
And I suddenly realized that for a robot
وفجأة أدركت أنه بالنسبه لروبوت
both information as well as food
كلا المعلومات والطعام
were the same thing.
كانا ذات الشئ
Energy came to it in some form or shape,
الطاقة جاءت إليه بهيئة أو شكل ما
data came to it in some form or shape.
وجاءت البيانات إليه بهيئة أو شكل ما
And I began to think,
و بدأت بالتفكير،
I wonder what it would be like
أتساءل ماذا سيكون الحال
to start imagining myself
لو تخيلت نفسي
as if energy and information were the two things I had as input --
كما لو كانت الطاقة والمعلومات الأمرين الذين أملك كمدخلات
as if food and information were similar in some form or shape.
كما لو كان الغذاء والمعلومات متماثلان بهيئةٍ أو شكلٍ ما
I started doing some research then, and this was the 25-year journey,
بدأت بالقيام ببعض البحوث، وكانت هذه رحلة ال25 عاماً،
and started finding out
وبدأت اكتشاف
that actually human beings as primates
أن البشر في الواقع كرئيسات
have far smaller stomachs
يملكون بطون أصغر بكثير
than should be the size for our body weight
مما ينبغي أن يكون الحجم بالنسبة لوزن أجسامنا
and far larger brains.
وعقول أكبر بكثير.
And as I went to research that even further,
وكلما تعمقت أكثر في بحث ذلك
I got to a point where I discovered something
وصلت إلى نقطة اكتشفت فيها شيئا
called the expensive tissue hypothesis.
يدعى فرضية الأنسجة باهظة الثمن.
That actually for a given body mass of a primate
أنه في الواقع لكتلة جسم معين من الرئيسات
the metabolic rate was static.
وكان معدل الأيض ثابت.
What changed was the balance of the tissues available.
ما تغير كان توازن الأنسجة الموجوده
And two of the most expensive tissues in our human body
واثنين من أغلى الأنسجة في الجسم البشري
are nervous tissue and digestive tissue.
هي الأنسجة العصبية وانسجه الجهاز الهضمي.
And what transpired was that people had put forward a hypothesis
وما حدث أن الناس قد طرحت فرضية
that was apparently coming up with some fabulous results by about 1995.
حيث جاءت كما يبدو ببعض النتائج الرائعة بحوالي عام 1995.
It's a lady named Leslie Aiello.
إنها سيدة تدعى ليزلي ايالو
And the paper then suggested that you traded one for the other.
واقترحت الورقة بانه يمكنك مبادلة أحدهما مع الآخر.
If you wanted your brain for a particular body mass to be large,
إذا كنت تريد عقلك لكتلة جسم معينة ان يكون كبير،
you had to live with a smaller gut.
عليك أن تعيش مع أمعاء أصغر.
That then set me off completely
حفّزني ذلك تماماً
to say, Okay, these two are connected.
لأن أقول، حسنا، هذان الاثنان مرتبطان.
So I looked at the cultivation of information as if it were food
لذا نظرت إلى التثقّف بالمعلومات كما لو كانت غذاء
and said, So we were hunter-gathers of information.
والقول،فنحن كنّا صيادين جامعين للمعلومات.
We moved from that to becoming farmers and cultivators of information.
انتقلنا من ذلك إلى أن امسينا فلاحين ومزارعين للمعلومات.
Does that really explain what we're seeing
هل حقا يفسر هذا ما نراه
with the intellectual property battles nowadays?
مع معارك الملكية الفكرية هذه الأيام؟
Because those people who were hunter-gatherers in origin
لأن أولئك الناس الذين كانوا جماعات الصيد والجني في الأصل
wanted to be free and roam and pick up information as they wanted,
أرادوا أن يكونوا أحراراً وأن يتجولوا ويلتقطوا المعلومات كما أرادوا،
and those that were in the business of farming information
وأولئك اللذين عملوا برعاية المعلومات
wanted to build fences around it,
أرادوا بناء الأسوار حولها
create ownership and wealth and structure and settlement.
إنشاء حق ملكية وثروة وبنية وتوطين
So there was always going to be a tension within that.
لذا سوف يكون هناك توتر ضمن ذلك
And everything I saw in the cultivation
وكل شيء قد رأيت في الزراعة
said there were huge fights amongst the foodies
أبدى أن هناك قتالاً عنيفاً بين البطينيين
between the cultivators and the hunter-gatherers.
بين المزارعين وجماعات الصيد والجني.
And this is happening here.
وهذا ما يحدث هنا.
When I moved to preparation, this same thing was true,
عندما انتقلت إلى الإعداد، الشيء نفسه كان صحيحاً،
expect that there were two schools.
الا ان هناك مدرستين.
One group of people said you can distill your information,
مجموعة من الناس قالت يمكنك تنقية معلوماتك،
you can extract value, separate it and serve it up,
يمكنك استخراج القيمة، وفصلها وتقديمها
while another group turned around
بينما جماعة أخرى خالفوا
and said no, no you can ferment it.
وقالوا لا لا، يمكنك يمكنك تخميرها.
You bring it all together and mash it up
يمكنك جمعها ومزجها
and the value emerges that way.
وتنتج القيمة بهذه الطريقة.
The same is again true with information.
ذات الشيء ينطبق أيضاً على المعلومات
But consumption was where it started getting really enjoyable.
ولكن بدأت المتعه الحقيقيه عند الاستهلاك
Because what I began to see then
لأن ما بدأت اراه لاحقا
was there were so many different ways people would consume this.
انه يوجد العديد من الطرق المختلفة التي يمكن للناس استهلاك هذا بها
They'd buy it from the shop as raw ingredients.
يمكنهم شرائها من المتجر كمواد خام.
Do you cook it? Do you have it served to you?
هل تطبخه؟ هل يقدم لك؟
Do you go to a restaurant?
هل تذهب إلى مطعم؟
The same is true every time as I started thinking about information.
ينطبق ذات الشيء دائما كلما فكرت في المعلومات.
The analogies were getting crazy --
صارت التشابهات الى حد الجنون
that information had sell-by dates,
ان المعلومات لها تاريخ انتهاء
that people had misused information that wasn't dated properly
أن الناس قد أسائوا استخدام المعلومات التي لم تكن مؤرخة بشكل صحيح
and could really make an effect on the stock market,
ويمكن حقا أن تؤثر على سوق الأوراق المالية،
on corporate values, etc.
قيم الشركات وما إلى ذلك.
And by this time I was hooked.
وبحلول هذا الوقت كنت مولعاً
And this is about 23 years into this process.
وهذا بمرور 23 عاماً في هذه العملية.
And I began to start thinking of myself
وبدأت بالتفكير في نفسي
as we start having mash-ups of fact and fiction,
حيث أننا بدأنا بالحصول على مزج بين الواقع والخيال
docu-dramas, mockumentaries, whatever you call it.
دراما وثائقية، السخرية الوثائقية، أيا ما تسمونه.
Are we going to reach the stage
هل سنصل إلى مرحلة
where information has a percentage for fact associated with it?
حينما تحتوي المعلومات على نسبة حقيقه مرتبطه بها؟
We start labeling information for the fact percentage?
نبدأ بتصنيف المعلومات حسب النسبة المئوية للحقيقة؟
Are we going to start looking at what happens
هل سنبدأ في النظر في ما سيحدث
when your information source is turned off, as a famine?
عندما يتم إيقاف مصدر المعلومات الخاصة بك، كمجاعة؟
Which brings me to the final element of this.
ذاك ما يقودني إلى العنصر الأخير من هذا.
Clay Shirky once stated that there is no such animal as information overload,
ذكر كلاي شيركي مرة أنه لا يوجد هناك حيوان يدعى فيض المعلومات
there is only filter failure.
هناك فشل تصفية فقط.
I put it to you that information,
وأنا أقول لكم ان المعلومات،
if viewed from the point of food,
إذا نظر إليها من وجهة نظر كالغذاء،
is never a production issue; you never speak of food overload.
ليست بتاتاً مسألة انتاجية ؛ لن تتحدث عنها كغذاء زائد
Fundamentally it's a consumption issue.
أساسا أنها قضية استهلاك.
And we have to start thinking
ويتعين علينا أن نبدأ في التفكير
about how we create diets within ourselves, exercise within ourselves,
حول كيف ننشئ حمية داخلنا، تمرين داخلنا،
to have the faculties to be able to deal with information,
لنتملك السبل لنكون قادرين على التعامل مع المعلومات
to have the labeling to be able to do it responsibly.
لنمتلك التصنيفات التي تمكننا من القيام بذلك بمسؤولية.
In fact, when I saw "Supersize Me," I starting thinking of saying,
في الواقع، عندما رأيت "كبّر حجمي" فكّرت أن أقول
What would happen
ما الذي سيحدث
if an individual had 31 days nonstop Fox News?
إذا كان لشخص ما 31 يوما لمتابعة "شبكة فوكس نيوز" بدون توقف ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Would there be time to be able to work with it?
هل سيكون هناك وقت ليكون قادرا على العمل بها؟
So you start really understanding
تبدأ فعليّاً بالفهم
that you can have diseases, toxins, a need to balance your diet,
أنه بالامكان أن تصاب بالأمراض، بالسموم، هناك حاجة إلى موازنة غذائك،
and once you start looking, and from that point on,
وعندها تبدا بالبحث، ومن تلك اللحظه
everything I have done in terms of the consumption of information,
كل ما قمت به من بالنسبة لاستهلاك المعلومات،
the production of information, the preparation of information,
إنتاج المعلومات، إعداد المعلومات،
I've looked at from the viewpoint of food.
أخذته من وجهة نظر وكأنّه طعام
It has probably not helped my waistline any
ربما لم يساعد محيط الخصر عندي
because I like practicing on both sides.
لأنني أحب ممارسة كلا الجانبين.
But I'd like to leave you with just that question:
ولكن أود أن اترككم فقط مع هذا السؤال:
If you began to think of all the information that you consume
إذا بدأت التفكر في جميع المعلومات التي تستهلكها
the way you think of food,
بنفس طريقة تفكيرك بالطعام
what would you do differently?
ما اللذي ستفعله بشكل مختلف؟
Thank you very much for your time.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر على وقتكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)